Now that you know how to load
现在 你已经学会了在Octave中
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
and save data in Octave, put
如何加载或存储数据
your data into matrices and so
如何把数据存入矩阵 等等
on. In this video I'd like
在这段视频中
to show you how to do computational
我将向你介绍
operations on data and
如何对数据进行运算
later on we'll be using this
稍后我们将使用这些
sorts of computation operations to implement our learning algorithms.
运算操作来实现我们的学习算法
Let's get started.
现在我们开始吧
Here's my Octave window.
这是我的 Octave 窗口
Let me just quickly initialize some
我现在快速地
variables to use
初始化一些变量
for examples and set A
比如设置A
to be a 3 by 2 matrix.
为一个3×2的矩阵
and set B to a
设置B为
3 by 2 matrix and let's
一个3 × 2矩阵
set C to a
设置C为
2 by 2 matrix, like so.
2 × 2矩阵
Now, let's say I want to multiply 2 of my matrices.
现在 我想算两个矩阵的乘积
So, let's say I wanna compute AxC.
比如说 A × C
I just type AxC.
我只需键入A×C
So, it's a 3 by 2 matrix times a 2 by 2 matrix.
这是一个 3×2 矩阵乘以 2×2 矩阵
This gives me this 3 by 2 matrix.
得到这样一个3×2矩阵
You can also do elements wise
你也可以对每一个元素
operations and do A.xB
做运算 方法是做点乘运算A .*B
and what this would do is
这么做
they'll take each elements of A
Octave将矩阵 A 中的每一个元素
and multiply it by
与矩阵 B 中的
the corresponding elements of B.
对应元素相乘
So, that's A, that's B, that's A.xB.
这是A 这是B 这是A .* B
So, for example, the first element
比如说 这里第一个元素
gives 1 times 11 which gives 11.
1乘以11得到11
The second element gives
第二个元素是
2 x 12 which gives 24 and so on.
2乘以12得到24
So it is the element
这就是两个矩阵的
wise multiplication of two
元素位运算
matrices, and in general
通常来说
the P rand tends to,
在Octave中
it's usually used, to denote
点号一般
element wise operations in octave.
用来表示元素位运算
So, here's a matrix
这里是一个矩阵A
A and I'll do A dot carry 2.
这里我输入A .^ 2
This gives me the multi,
这将对矩阵A中
the element wise squaring of
每一个元素平方
A, so 1 squared
所以 1的平方是1
is 1, 2 squared is 4 and so on.
2的平方是4 等等
Let's set V to a vector,
我们设V是一个向量
we'll set V as 123 as a column vector.
设V为 [1; 2; 3] 是列向量
You can also do 1.
你也可以输入
over V to do
1 ./ V
the element wise reciprocal of
得到每一个元素的倒数
V so this gives me
所以这样一来
one over one, one over two and one over three.
就会分别算出 1/1  1/2  1/3
This works too for matrices so
矩阵也可以这样操作
one dot over A, gives me
1 ./ A 得到
that element wise inverse of
A中每一个元素的倒数
A.  and once
同样地
again the P radians gives use
这里的点号
a clue that this is an elements wise operation.
还是表示对每一个元素进行操作
To also do things like log
我们还可以进行求对数运算
V This is an element wise
也就是对每个元素
logarithm of, the
进行求对数运算
V, E to the
还有自然数e的幂次运算
V, is the base E
就是以e为底
exponentiation of these elements
以这些元素为幂的运算
of this is E, this is E
所以这是e 这是e的平方
squared EQ, this is
这是e的立方
V. And I
v 矩阵是这样的
can also do apps V to
我还可以用 abs
take the element wise absolute
来对 v 的每一个元素
value of V. So here,
求绝对值
V was all positive, abs, say
当然这里 v 都是正数
minus 1 to minus 3,
我们换成另一个
the element wise Absolute
这样对每个元素求绝对值
value gives me back these
得到的结果就是
non-negative values and negative
这些非负的元素
V gives me the minus
还有 -v
of V. This is the same
给出V中每个元素的相反数
as -1xV but usually
这等价于 -1 乘以 v
you just write negative V and
不过一般就直接用 -v 就好了
so that negative 1xV and what else can you do?
其实就等于 -1*v
Here's another neat trick.
还有什么呢？
So Let's see.
还有一个技巧
Let's say I want to take V and increment each of these elements by 1.
比如说 我们想对v中的每个元素都加1
Well, one way to do
那么我们可以这么做
it is by constructing a
首先构造一个
3 by 1 vector
3行1列的1向量
this all ones and adding that to V. So, they do that.
然后把这个1向量跟原来的向量相加
This increments V by for 123 to 234.
因此 v 向量从[1 2 3] 增至 [2 3 4]
The way I did
我用了一个
that was length of V, is three.
length(v) 命令
So ones, length of
因此这样一来
V by one, this is ones
ones(length(v) ,1) 就相当于
of three by one.
ones(3,1)
So that's ones, three by one.
所以这是ones(3,1)
On the right and what I
对吧 然后我做的是
did was B plus ones,
v + ones(3,1)
V by one, which is adding
也就是将 v 的各元素
this vector of all ones
都加上这些1
to B. And so this increments
这样就将 v 的每个元素
V by one.
增加了1
And you, another simpler
另一种更简单的方法是
way to do that is to type V+ one, right?
直接用 v+1
So that's V and
所以这是 v
V+ one also means to
v + 1 也就等于
add one element wise to
把 v 中的每一个元素
each of my elements of V.
都加上1
Now, let's talk about more operations.
现在 让我们来谈谈更多的操作
So, here's my matrix A. If you want to write A transpose.
这是我的矩阵A 如果你想要求它的转置
The way to do that is to write A prime.
那么方法是用A‘
That's the apostrophe symbol.
这是单引号符号
It's the left quote.
并且是左引号
So, on your keyboard
可能你的键盘上
you probably have a left
有一个左引号
quote and a right quote.
和一个右引号
So this is a at the
这里用的是左引号
standard quotation mark is a,
也就是标准的引号
what to say, a transpose
因此 A’
to excuse me the, you
将得出 A 的转置矩阵
know, a transpose of my
当然
major and of course
如果我写 (A‘)’
a transpose if I transpose
也就是 A 转置两次
that again then I should
那么我又重新得到矩阵 A
get back my matrix A. Some more useful functions.
还有一些有用的函数
Let's say locate A is
假如说 小写a
1 15 to 0.5.
是[1 15 2 0.5]
So, it's a, you know, 1 by 4 matrix.
这是一个1行4列矩阵
Let's say set val equals max
假如说 val=max(a)
of A.  This returns the
这将返回
maximum value of A, which
A矩阵中的最大值
in this case is 15 and
在这里是15
I can do val ind max
我还可以写 [val, ind] = max(a)
A.  And this returns
这将返回
val of int which are
a矩阵中的最大值
the maximum value of A
存入val
which is 15 as was the index.
以及该值对应的索引
So the elements number two of A that 15.
因此元素15对应的索引值为2 存入ind
So, in is my index into this.
所以 ind 等于2
Just as a warning: if
特别注意一下
you do max A where A is a matrix.
如果你用命令 max(A) A是一个矩阵的话
What this does is this actually
这样做就是对每一列
does the column wise maximum,
求最大值
but say a little bit more about this in a second.
等下再仔细讲讲
So, using this example of the
我们还是用这个例子
variable lowercase A. If I do A less than three.
这个 小a 矩阵
This does the element wise operation.
如果输入 a<3
Element wise comparison.
这将进行逐元素的运算
So, the first element
所以 第一个元素
Of A is less than three equals to one.
是小于3的 因此返回1
Second elements of A is
a的第二个元素
not less than three, so
不小于3 所以
this value is zero, because it is also.
这个值是0 表示"非"
The third and fourth numbers of
第三个和第四个数字
A are the lesson,
仍然是小于3
I meant less than three, third and fourth elements are less than three.
2和0.5都小于3
So this is one, one, so
因此 这返回[1 1 0 1]
this is just the element wide
也就是说
comparison of all four
对a矩阵的每一个元素
element variable lower case
与3进行比较
three and it returns true
然后根据每一个元素与3的大小关系
or false depending on whether or not it's less than three.
返回1和0表示真与假
Now, if I do find
现在 如果我写 find(a<3)
A less than three, this would
这将告诉我
tell me which are the
a 中的哪些元素
elements of A that the
是小于3的
variable A of less than three
and in this case the 1st, 3rd
在这里就是第一 第三和第四个元素
and 4th elements are lesson three.
是小于3的
For my next example Oh, let
下一个例子
me set eight be code to
设A = magic(3)
magic three. The magic
magic 函数返回什么呢
function returns. Let's type help magic.  Functions called
让我们查看 magic 函数的帮助文件
The magic function returns.
magic 函数将返回
Returns this matrices called magic squares.
一个矩阵 称为魔方阵或幻方 (magic squares)
They have this, you know,
它们具有以下
mathematical property that all
这样的数学性质
of their rows and columns and
它们所有的行和列和对角线
diagonals sum up to the same thing.
加起来都等于相同的值
So, you know, it's
当然据我所知
not actually useful for machine
这在机器学习里
learning as far as I
基本用不上
know, but I'm just using
但我可以用这个方法
this as a convenient way,
很方便地生成一个
you know, to generate a 3
3行3列的矩阵
by 3 matrix and this magic square screen.
而这个魔方矩阵这神奇的方形屏幕。
We have the power of 3
每一行 每一列
at each row, each column and
每一个对角线
the diagonals all add up
三个数字加起来
to the same thing, so it's kind of a mathematical construct.
都是等于同一个数
I use magic, I use this
我只有在演示功能
magic function only when I'm
或者上课教 Octave 的时候
doing demos, or when I'm
会用到这个矩阵
teaching Octave like this and
在其他有用的机器学习应用中
I don't actually use it for
这个矩阵其实没多大作用
any, you know, useful machine learning application.
让我来看看别的
But, let's see, if I type RC equals find A greater than or equals 7.
如果我输入 [r,c] = find( A>=7 )
This finds all the elements
这将找出所有A矩阵中
of a that are greater than
大于等于7的元素
and equals to 7 and
因此
so, RC sense a row and column.
r 和 c 分别表示行和列
So, the 11 element is greater than 7.
这就表示 第一行第一列的元素大于等于7
The three two elements is
第三行第二列的元素大于等于7
greater than 7 and the two 3 elements is greater than 7.
第二行第三列的元素大于等于7
So let's see, the two, three
我们来看看 第二行第三列的元素
element for example, is A two, three.
就是 A(2,3)
Is seven, is this element
是等于7的
out here, and that is indeed greater than or equal seven.
就是这个元素 确实是大于等于7的
By the way, I actually don't even
顺便说一句 其实我从来都
memorize myself what these
不去刻意记住这个 find 函数
find functions do in the
到底是怎么用的
all these things do myself and
我只需要会用 help 函数就可以了
whenever I use a find
每当我在使用这个函数
function, sometimes I forget
忘记怎么用的时候
myself exactly what does, and
我就可以用 help 函数
you know, type help find to look up the document.
键入 help find 来找到帮助文档
Okay, just two more things, if it's okay, to show you.
好吧 最后再讲两个内容
One is the sum function.
一个是求和函数
So here's my A and
这是 a 矩阵
I type sum A. This adds
键入 sum(a)
up all the elements of A.
就把 a 中所有元素加起来了
And if I want to multiply them
如果我想把它们都乘起来
together, I type prod A.
键入 prod(a)
Prod sense of product,
prod 意思是 product(乘积)
and it returns the products of
它将返回
these four elements of A.
这四个元素的乘积
Floor A rounds down,
floor(a) 是向下四舍五入
these elements of A, so zero
因此对于 a 中的元素
O point five gets rounded down to zero.
0.5将被下舍入变成0
And ceil, or ceiling A,
还有 ceil(A)
gets rounded up, so zero
表示向上四舍五入
point five, rounded up to
所以0.5将上舍入变为
the nearest integer, so zero point five gets rounded up to one.
最接近的整数 也就是1
You can also.
还有
Let's see.
我们来看
Let me type rand 3.
键入 type(3)
This generally sets a 3 by 3 matrix.
这通常得到一个3×3的矩阵
If I type max randd 3, rand 3.
如果键入 max(rand(3), rand(3))
What this does is it takes
这样做的结果是
the element wise maximum of
返回两个3×3的随机矩阵
2 random 3 by 3 matrices.
并且逐元素比较 取最大值
So, you'll notice all these
所以 你会发现所有这些
numbers tend to be a bit on the
数字几乎都比较大
large side because each of
因为这里的每个元素
these is actually the max of
都实际上是
a randomly, of element Y's
两个随机生成的矩阵
max of two randomly generated matrices.
逐元素进行比较 取最大的那个值
This is my magic number.
这是刚才生成的
This was my magic square 3x3a.
3×3魔方阵 A
Let's say I type max A and then this will be it.
假如我输入
Open, close, square brackets comma 1.
max(A,[],1)
What this does is
这样做会得到
this takes the column wise maximum.
每一列的最大值
So, the maximum of the
所以第一例的最大值
first column is eight, max
就是8
of the second column is nine,
第二列是9
the max of the third column is seven.
第三列的最大值是7
This 1 means to take the
这里的1表示
max along the first dimension of
取A矩阵第一个维度的最大值
A.  In contrast, if
相对地
I were to type max a, this
如果我键入
funny notation 2 then this
max(A,[],2)
takes the per row maximum.
这将得到每一行的最大值
So, the maximum for the first
所以 第一行的最大值
row is 8, max of
是等于8
second row is 7, max
第二行最大值是7
of the third row is 9
第三行是9
and so this allows you to take maxes.
所以你可以用这个方法
You know, per row or per column.
来求得每一行或每一列的最值
And if you want to, and
另外
remember it defaults to column
你要知道 默认情况下
mark wise elements on this,
max(A)返回的是
so if you want to find
每一列的最大值
the maximum element in
如果你想要
the entire matrix A, you
找出整个矩阵A的最大值
can type max of max
你可以输入
of A, like so, which is nine.
max(max(A)) 像这样
Or you can turn A into
或者你可以将 A 矩阵转成
a vector and type max
一个向量
of A colon, like
然后键入 max(A(:))
so, this treats this as a vector
这样做就是把 A 当做一个向量
and takes the max element of vector.
并返回 A 向量中的最大值
Finally, let's set A
最后 让我们把 A 设为一个
to be a nine by nine magic square.
9行9列的魔方阵
So remember, the magic square
别忘了
has this property that every
魔方阵具有的特性是
column in every row sums the same thing and also the diagonals.
每行每列和对角线的求和都是相等的
So here is 9X9 magic square.
这是一个9×9的魔方阵
So let me just sum A one
我们来求一个 sum(A,1)
so this does a per column sum.
这样就得到每一列的总和
And so I'm going to take each
所以这样做就是
column of A and add
把 A 的每一列进行求和
them up and this, you
从这里我们也可以看出
know, lets us verify that indeed
这也验证了
for 9 by 9 magic square.
一个9×9的魔方阵
Every column adds up to 369 as of the same thing.
确实每一列加起来都相等 都为369
Now, let's do the row wise sum.
现在我们来求每一行的和
So, the sum A  comma 2
键入sum(A,2)
and this sums
这样就得到了
up each row of A
A 中每一行的和
and each row of A
also sums up to 369.
加起来还是369
Now let's sum the
现在我们来算
diagonal elements of A
A 的对角线元素的和
and make sure that they, that
看看它们的和
that also sums up to the same thing.
是不是也相等
So what I'm going to
我们现在构造一个
do is, construct a nine
9×9 的单位矩阵
by nine identity matrix, that's
键入 eye(9)
I9, and let me
设为I9
take A and construct, multiply
然后我们要用 A
A elements wise.
逐点乘以这个单位矩阵
So here's my matrix of A.
这是矩阵A
I'm gonna do A.xI9 and what
我现在用 A 逐点乘以 eye(9)
this will do is take the
这样做的结果是
element wise product of these
两个矩阵对应元素
2 matrices, and so this
将进行相乘
should wipe out everything except
除了对角线元素外
for the diagonal entries and now
其他元素都会得到0
I'm going to sum, sum of
然后我对刚才求到的结果
A of that and this
键入sum(sum(A.*eye(9))
gives me the sum of
这实际上是求得了
these diagonal elements, and indeed it is 369.
这个矩阵对角线元素的和 确实是369
You can sum up the other diagonal as well.
你也可以求另一条对角线的和
So this top left to bottom right.
这个是从左上角到右下角的
You can sum up the opposite diagonal
你也可以求另一条对角线
from bottom left to top right.
从左下角到右上角
The sum, the commands for this is somewhat more cryptic.
这个和  这个命令会有点麻烦
You don't really need to know this.
其实你不需要知道这个
I'm just showing you just in
我只是想给你看
case any of you are curious,
如果你感兴趣的话可以听听
but let's see.
让我们来看看
Flip UD stands for flip up/down.
flipup/flipud 表示向上/向下翻转
If you do that, that turns out
如果你用这个命令的话
to sum up the
计算的就是副对角线上
elements in the opposites of,
所有元素的和
the other diagonal that also sums up to 369.
还是会得到369
Here, let me show you,
我来给你演示一下
whereas i9 is this
eye(9) 矩阵是这样
matrix, flip up/down of
那么 flipup(eye(9))
i9, you know, takes the identity
将得到一个单位矩阵
matrix and flips it vertically
并且将它翻转
so you end up with, excuse me,
不好意思打错了
flip UD, end up
应该是flipud
with ones on this opposite diagonal as well.
翻转以后所有的1就变成副对角线了
Just one last command and then
最后再说一个命令
that's it, and then that will be it for this video.
然后就下课
Let's say A to be the
假如 A 是一个
3x3 magic square
3×3的魔方阵
again. If you want
同样地 如果你想
to invert the matrix, you
这个矩阵的逆矩阵
type P inv A, this
键入 pinv(A)
is typically called a pseudo inference, but it doesn't matter.
通常称为伪逆矩阵 但这个名字不重要
Think of it as basically the inverse
你就把它看成是
of A and that's the
矩阵 A 求逆
inverse of A and second
因此这就是 A 矩阵的逆矩阵
set, you know, 10 equals p
设 temp = pinv(A)
of A and of temp times
然后再用temp 乘以 A
A. This is indeed the
这实际上得到的就是
identity matrix with essentially ones
单位矩阵
on the diagonals and zeros on
对角线为1 其他元素为0
the off-diagonals, up to a numerical round-off.
稍微圆整一下就是
So, that's it for how
好了 这样我们就介绍了
to do different computational operations
如何对矩阵中的数字
on the data in matrices.
进行各种操作
And after running a
在运行完某个
learning algorithm, often one of
学习算法之后
the most useful things is to
通常一件最有用的事情
be able to look at your
是看看你的结果
results, or to plot, or visualize your result.
或者说让你的结果可视化
And in the next video I'm
在接下来的视频中
going to very quickly show you
我会非常迅速地告诉你
how, again, with one or
如何很快地画出
two lines of code using Octave
如何只用一两行代码
you can quickly visualize your
你就可以快速地可视化你的数据
data, or plot your data
画出你的数据
and use that to better
这样你就能更好地理解
understand, you know, what your learning algorithms are doing.
你使用的学习算法 (字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )